Ozan Sener, www.ozansener.net

CONTACT INFORMATION 133 Gates Hall, 353 Serra Mall Stanford University, CA 94305 voice: +1 607 379 47 39 e-mail: ozan@cs.stanford.edu

INTEREST

Broadly, I am interested in designing machine learning algorithms which can process large-amount of multi-modal information with no/weak supervision. I have designed algorithms which scaled to tens of thousands of videos, point clouds with hundreds of millions of points and deployed them in robots, mobile devices and homes. I mostly worked on classification/parsing/segmentation problems in robot perception and mobile multimedia, using graphical models, metric learning and deep learning. In general, I am interested in any problem related to machine learning and large-scale data.

EDUCATION

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

December 2016 GPA: 4.00/4.00

PhD in Computer Engineering Advisor: Ashutosh Saxena

Thesis: Learning from large-scale visual data for robots.

Middle East Technical University, Ankara, Turkey June 2012

BS and MS in Electrical and Electronics Engineering GPA: 3.93(MS), 3.88(BS)/4.00

Advisor: Aydın Alatan

An Efficient Graph-Theoretical Approach for Interactive Mobile Image & Video Segmentation

HONOURS AND AWARDS

10 Breakthrough Technologies in 2016 by MIT Technology Review (Robots sharing knowledge)	2016
Jacobs Scholar Fellowship	2013
METU Best Master Thesis Award	2012 – 2013
IEEE-eXtreme Programming Competition 5.0, (1st place Nationwide, 8th place Europe)	2012
METU Electrical Engineering Bachelor Thesis Award	2010
XPLORE New Automation Award (Top 17 projects worldwide in the category of recreation)	2009
IEEE Foundation Grant Recipient	2009
Chairperson, IEEE Computer Society METU Student Branch	2007 - 2008
Dr Bulent Kerim Altay Award (given by the METU EE Department to the student who ranks first in his/her class)	2006 – 2007
National Olympiad in Informatics (Regional degree - 1st place)	2004

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Stanford University, CA

December 2016 - Present

Post Doctoral Researcher

Advised by Prof. Silvio Savarese.

Worked on the geometrical understanding of deep learning architectures. Studied the geometry of feature spaces learned by convolutional neural networks (CNNs) which resulted in a theoretical understanding of generalization properties of CNNs *in Submission*. Further extended these results to transfer learning problems and developed a domain adaptation (*in NIPS 2016*) and active learning algorithm (*in Submission*) with theoretical guarantees.

Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Stanford University, CA

August 2014 - December 2016

Visiting Scholar

Advised by Prof. Silvio Savarese and Prof. Ashutosh Saxena.

Worked on large-scale machine learning algorithms for computer vision.

Developed a transductive machine learning algorithm for unsupervised domain adaptation problem. The resulting algorithm enables machine learning models to be trained on one domain and used in other ones (in NIPS 2016).

Developed a structured parsing algorithm which can parse large point clouds of buildings into its semantic elements near real time. (in CVPR 2016).

Developed a large-scale, unsupervised video understanding framework using category specific youtube videos. The resulting algorithm can parse large collection of videos by discovering the underlying activities. (in ICCV 2015).

Robot Learning Research Group, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY

August 2013 - August 2014

Research Assistant

Advised by Prof. Ashutosh Saxena.

Studied graphical models from an efficiency perspective. Developed a geometric framework for efficient and explicit approximations of probability distributions over high dimensional spaces. Using the developed geometric understanding, proposed a novel inference mechanism -rCRF- in order to efficiently, accurately and explicitly represent a belief over any CRF model using structured diversity (*in RSS 2015 and an invited talk at AAAI 2016*). Further extended the developed geometric approach to efficient learning algorithm for graphical models with hidden nodes and non-parametric priors (*in the process of submission*).

Designed a large-scale multi-modal processing and storage system which scales to millions of videos, images and text as a part of the RoboBrain (www.robobrain.me) project (in ISRR 2015).

Multimedia Research Group, METU, Ankara, Turkey

February 2011 – August 2013

Research Assistant

Worked in collaboration with Nokia Research Center, Tampere.

Advised by Prof. Aydın Alatan (METU) and Dr. Kemal Ugur (Nokia Research Center, Tampere).

Developed an efficient interactive video segmentation algorithm via Markov random field energy propagation. Proposed a dynamic method to reuse residual-flows in filtering scenario for time efficiency (in Transaction on Multimedia 2013).

Developed a method efficiently solving interactive image segmentation problem via dynamic and iterative graph-cuts. Furthermore, improved the robustness of the method via automatic correction of user interaction errors (in ACM-MM-W 2012, ICIP 2012).

Involved in patent application and deployed part of the developed algorithms to production on Nokia N9.

Siemens Corporate Research, Princeton, NJ

August 2010 – February 2011

Research Intern in Imaging, Analytics and Informatics Department Advised by Dr. Bogdan Georgescu and Dr. Yang Wang

Contributed to the development of the LVA(Left Ventricle Anatomy) software. Developed a learning based method for automatic classification of volume contrast echocardiography data.

Signal Processing Laboratory 4, EPFL, Switzerland

July 2009 – September 2009

Research Intern

Advised by Prof. Pascal Frossard

Worked on the similarity analysis of observations under affine projections. Developed a distance metric to be used in multi-view classification problems. Implemented and tested proposed distance metric in graph based multi-view object classification algorithm.

PRE-PRINTS

- O. Sener, S. Savarese. A Geometric Approach to Active Learning for Convolutional Neural Networks. In *Submission*.
- H. Wang, S. Pirk, O. Sener, E. Yumer, V. Kim, L. Guibas. Learning to Generate Multi-Step Human-Object Interactions from Videos. In *Submission*.

PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

- O. Sener, H. O. Song, A. Saxena, S. Savarese. Learning Transferrable Representations for Unsupervised Domain Adaptation. In *Neural Information Processing Systems*, *NIPS 2016*.
- I. Armeni, O. Sener, A. Zamir, S. Savarese. 3D Semantic Parsing of Large-Scale Indoor Spaces. In *Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, CVPR 2016 (oral)*.
- O. Sener, A. Zamir, S. Savarese, A. Saxena. Unsupervised Semantic Parsing of Video Collections. In *International Conference on Computer Vision, ICCV 2015*.
- O. Sener, A. Saxena. rCRF: Recursive Estimation of the Beliefs over CRFs for Activity Analysis in RGB-D Videos. In *Robotics Science and Systems, RSS 2015*.
- C. Wu, J. Zhang, O. Sener, B. Selman, S. Savarese, A. Saxena Watch-n-Patch: Unsupervised Learning of Actions and Relations. In *Multimedia*, *IEEE Transactions on*, vol. 16, no. 5, pp. 1292–1302, Aug 2014.
- A. Saxena, A. Jain, O. Sener, A. Jami, DK. Misra, HS. Koppula. RoboBrain: Large-Scale Knowledge Engine for Robots. In *International Symposium on Robotics Research, ISRR 2015*.
- O. Sener, K. Ugur, A. A. Alatan. Efficient MRF Energy Propagation for Video Segmentation via Bilateral Filters. In *Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence, IEEE Transactions on*, vol. PP, no. 99, pp.
- Y. Aksoy. O. Sener, A. A. Alatan, K. Ugur. Interactive 2d-3d image conversion for mobile devices. In *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing*, 2012.
- O. Sener, K. Ugur, A. A. Alatan. Error-tolerant interactive image segmentation using dynamic and iterated graph-cuts. In *Proceedings of the 2nd international workshop on Interactive multimedia on mobile and portable devices*, ACM Multimedia Workshop.
- O. Sener, K. Ugur, A. A. Alatan. Robust interactive segmentation via coloring. In *Proceedings of the 1st International Workshop on Visual Interfaces for Ground Truth Collection in Computer Vision Applications*, ACM AVI 2012 Workshop.

PATENTS

- A. Saxena, HS. Koppula, C. Wu, and O. Sener. Automatically learning and controlling connected devices. United States Patent Application, 20160248847
- K. Ugur, O. Sener, E. Gundogdu, and A. Alatan. Interactive Image/Video Segmentation For Mobile 2D/3D Conversion. International Patent Application, WO 2013144418 A1

RELATED COURSEWORK **Machine Learning:** Advanced Topics in Machine Learning c , Algorithmic Perspective on Machine Learning s , Hierarchies of Integer Programming Relaxations s , Pattern Recognition m , Artificial Intelligence m , Statistical Techniques in Mobile Robotics m

Probability and Stochastic Processes: Measure Theoretic Probability c , Applied Stochastic Processes c , Signal Analysis and Processing m , Adaptive Signal Processing m , Information Theory m

Analysis and Algebra: Analysis c , Matrix Computations c , Linear System Theory m , Functional Analysis and Operator Theory with App. m

Offered by ^sStanford University, ^cCornell University and ^mMiddle East Technical University.

Professional Activities

Service: Reviewer for NIPS, ICCV, CVPR, ICRA, WACV, Signal Processing Letters, T-MM, T-PAMI, CVIU. Organizer for Workshop on Negative Results in Computer Vision in cunjuction CVPR 2017.

Memberships: Student member of IEEE (since 2006) and ACM (since 2008)

Leadership: Chairperson of IEEE Computer Society METU Student Branch (2007-2008)

SKILLS

Python (proficient packages: Tensorflow and Numpy), C/C++ (proficient libraries: OpenCV and Boost), Matlab, LTFX, Git, GNU/Linux (personal usage and system administration on Debian based distros).

INTERESTS

Juggling (performed at METU Juggling Convention 2011&2012, attended European Juggling Convention 2011&2012, Founded Cornell Juggling Club), **Math Puzzles & Games** (game designer for EU Youth Action Project - Puzzle Puzzle 2007, finalist for World Puzzle Federation - Turkey Competition).

CITIZENSHIP Turkish LANGUAGE English and Turkish DATE OF BIRTH September 07, 1988